# Michael Welles

201 Eastern Parkway Apt. 3E Brooklyn, NY 11238 **☎** 917-586-9218 ⋈ mlwelles@gmail.com

## Overview

Years of experience leading technology teams on projects from conception to completion. Focus on mobile, emerging technologies, and digital media. Comfortable working at both the micro level (building container/codec/format internals) and the macro level (building highly available and scalable platforms for digestion, management, transformation, distribution, and consumption of media).

# Work Experience

#### 2017 - Director of Engineering (Mobile), MediData, New York, NY.

Present Led engineering teams responsible for Patient Cloud platform enabling the gathering of clinical trial data directly from patients and clinicians on mobile devices and wearable devices by patients and clinicians on mobile devices. Products include ePRO, the iOS and Android application used for patient reported outcomes, Patient Cloud, an iOS tablet application for clinician reported outcomes clinicians at study sites, AppConnect a native SDK for use by third party iOS and Android developers, Sensor Link, for the direct ingestion of data from wearable sensors, as well as the backend platform responsible the for the collection and processing of clinical data from these applications. Launched two new major mobile product initiatives, migrated all native mobile development to Swift and Kotlin, built real time compliance dashboards for data reporting, introduced workflow and organizational improvements that led to a doubling of average team velocity.

#### 2013 - 2016 Director of Mobile, Huge, Brooklyn, NY.

First as principal architect, then engineering director, focusing on mobile and emerging technologies. In most recent role, head 20+ person cross-functional team of iOS, Android, and backend engineers - as well as QA analysts, designers, and product managers. Institute and evangelize agile best practices, continuous integration, and continuous delivery. Sponsor new technology investigations and initiatives (interior way-finding, Leap Motion, Arduino, and embedded system prototypes), as well as internal outreach initiatives (meetups, open source efforts, etc.). Notable client work include 'smart' bluetooth audio/video accessories that support live video streaming and voice commands, among other features, and a companion application for an AAA game publisher that allows players to scan their own likeness to be rendered as an in-game ayatar, as well as numerous BTB and BTC mobile commerce applications.

### 2011 - 2013 Manager of Mobile Technology, Consumer Reports, Yonkers, NY.

Founded mobile applications and new media group. Built in-house team responsible for mobile applications development. Responsibilities included overall mobile product strategies and technical execution. Launched flagship ratings application and managed external vendors in the maintenance of a portfolio of legacy applications.

2008 - 2011 Senior Software Engineer - iTunes Store Video Workflow Group, Apple, Cupertino, CA.

Senior engineer on a team of five responsible for the encoding and assembly of all iTunes video media. Responsible for the encoding toolchain used by the processing cluster, as well as for the specification of formats of deliverable media, the test suites to validate the formats, and the creation of reference media for use by hardware teams in compliance testing. Heavily involved in the continuous improvement, day-to-day operations, business production, and engineering of the visual and audio quality of Store media. Led two major rewrites of the video workflow - the first for the launch of the HDTV product and the second for the launch of international video and television.

2007 - 2008 Senior Software Architect, The New York Times, New York, NY.

Led effort to incorporate continuous integration into the development and release processes of NYTimes.com. Created tools, procedures, and processes for the testing and packaging of software through the chain of production. Authored tools to help with process automation. Supervised overall architectural design for the effort to develop a new content management system for news.

2006 - 2007 Founder, Senior Partner, Bangstate, New York, NY.

Resumed role as senior partner, concentrating on web application using Ruby on Rails and other open source technologies. Strong focus on best practices, test-driven development, short milestones, iterative development, and close client interaction. Also served as acting CTO for haystack.com, a social networking site focused on music discovery and full album streaming content. In that role, led five person design and development team.

2004 - 2006 Systems Architect/Lead Developer, The Associated Press, New York, NY.

Designed and developed highly trafficked and dynamic systems for the distribution, digestion, and display of multimedia news content. Led team of seven developers, QA staff, and system engineers. Notable project was the development of AP Hosted Elections, a system that gathered, processed, and presented the up-to-the minute results of for the 2004 US presidential elections, which served as the sole source of 2004 presidential election data for all major US news organizations.

1998 - 2004 Founder, Senior Partner, Bangstate, New York, NY.

Founded and managed a consultancy of five principal partners, and ten additional developers, designers, and administrators. Responsible for the business as a whole, as well as delivering individual projects. Clients included organizations such as The Associated Press, The American Bar Association, Atlantic Records, Forbes Magazine, CIR/SEIU, Time, Inc. Notable projects included: TNEWS, the Internet distribution platform of the Associated Press that used standards-based protocols (NNTP, IPTC NITF XML) to distribute content that had previously only been available in proprietary formats over satellite and developing handheld applications for use by Military Family Research Institute at Purdue University.

- 1996 1997 Member, Technical Staff, SOS Corp, New York, NY.
- 1995 1996 System Administrator Distributed Resources Management, Paine Webber, New York, NY.
  - 1995 Consultant/Programmer, onShore, Chicago, IL.
  - 1994 Jr. Programmer/Analyst, The Social Science and Public Policy Computing Center at the University of Chicago, Chicago, IL.

## Education

1990 - 1994 Bachelor of Arts in History, The University of Chicago, Chicago, IL.

# Skills

Languages Swift, Objective-C, C, C++, Javascript, Ruby, Java, C#, Python, Lua, Lisp

Systems Experience with almost every flavor of Unix, deep knowledge of Linux/BSD/OSX/Unix internals, iOS, Android.

Media QuickTime, H.264, MPEG-4, MPEG-2, JPEG, TIFF, AAC, MP3, WAV, AIFF

# **OSS** Software

OSS contributions not otherwise noted in work history;

- Author, BeaconScanner, desktop utility for OSX for detecting and managing iBeacons. http://tinyurl.com/j6rpfbc (2014)
- Maintainer of libtiff. http://www.libtiff.org/ (1999-2001)
- Contributor to the Debian bootfloppy project
- Author of the changedfiles system, a combination of a kernel module and a user space client that provided real time notification of file system modifications and offered programatic hooks for any arbitrary actions to be taken in response. Included inline support for triggering filesystem replication by via rsync, and FTP, as well as mysql database import. Became obsolete with the introduction of DBUS to the Linux kernel